Guide to the Religious Education Association Records
Yale University Divinity School Library
Religious Education Association Records
1902-1982
RG 74
Yale University Divinity School Library
55
(131 boxes)
These are the official archives of the Religious Education Association. The Religious Education Association was founded in 1903 at a convention in Chicago, which had been convened by the Council of Seventy of the American Institute of Sacred Literature Its goal has been to promote religious and moral education. The R.E.A. has produced many publications and has sponsored conventions and round tables on religion and higher education, as well as a major program of research on religious development. The R.E.A. was responsible for forming the National Council on Religion and Public Education.
Religious Education Association
Conditions Governing Access
Open to qualified researchers.
Immediate Source of Acquisition
Deposited by the R.E.A.
Biographical / Historical
The call to the founding convention of the Religious Education Association was issued in 1902 by the Council of Seventy, a core group of Biblical scholars and teachers in the American Institute of Sacred Literature. The leader of the group was William Rainey Harper, the first president of the University of Chicago, who was an outstanding Hebrew scholar and editor of the journal, Biblical World. The Convention was held in Chicago on February 10-12, 1903, and among the speakers were George Albert Coe and John Dewey. Frank K. Sanders, Dean of Yale Divinity School, was elected the first President of the Association, and Dr. Harper became chairman of the Executive Board. The R.E.A. was incorporated under the laws of the State of Illinois for the purpose, "to promote religious and moral education."
Other early conventions were held in Philadelphia (1904), Boston (1905), Rochester, NY (1907), and Washington, D.C. (1908), and bound proceedings were published and widely distributed. The famous three-fold purpose was adopted at the 1905 Convention in Boston: "to inspire the educational forces of our country with the religious ideal; to inspire the religious forces of our country with the educational ideal; and to keep before the public mind the ideal of Religious Education, and the sense of its need and value."
From 1903 to 1906, five Official Bulletins were published, but they were replaced by the journal, Religious Education, which began in April 1906 under the leadership of the organization's first permanent General Secretary, Henry F. Cope. During the first three decades of its life, the Association influenced the religious education movement in many ways, but upon the death of Dr. Cope in 1923, there were those who felt that the R.E.A. had accomplished its purpose and should go out of existence. The Institute of Social and Religious Research recommended its continuation as a "professional organization of high value, a forum of free discussion, a meeting place for education of all faiths, a common ground for character education, and an opportunity for pioneer inquiry and experimentation."
Between 1926 and 1934, the Association prospered with increased membership and grants from the Rockefeller and Carnegie funds. The journal became a monthly, a series of monographs was published, annual research conferences were held, and the Association co-sponsored the Character Education Inquiry project. On the initiative of Joseph Artman, General Secretary, a new bi-monthly magazine, Character was launched in 1934. Because the economic depression made it impossible to maintain two publications, no issues of the journal Religious Education were published between June 1934 and July 1935. With the resignation of Dr. Artman in 1935, all rights to the magazine were transferred to him and the journal was resumed under the editorship of Laird Hites and, later, Leonard Stidley.
The Association carried on with volunteer leadership until 1950, when a Mid-Century Expansion Fund raised the budget to call Harrison Elliott as the full-time executive. His sudden death a year later and the death that same year of Dr. Coe, who had been honorary President since 1938, meant the passing of two "giants" of the movement. A new era began with the election of Herman Wornom as General Secretary in 1952. The office was moved from Chicago to New York City; foundation and individual gifts provided a stronger financial base; and the 50th anniversary was celebrated at a convention in 1953 in Pittsburgh. Randolph Crump Miller began a 20-year tenure as editor of the journal. During the 1950s, there was a series of round tables and publications on religion and higher education, and the beginning of a series of well-attended conventions in Chicago. A long-range, five-stage program of research on religious development was funded by the Lilly Endowment. Merton Strommen was called as research director, the Lilly Research Training Fellowships were established, a 12-day workshop was held at Cornell, and the project was completed with the publication in 1971 of the book, Research on Religious Development. Chapters were developed in many cities under the leadership of Dr. Wornom and Wilson Cheek, Associate General Secretary from 1965 to 1967.
Under a new General Secretary, Boardman Kathan, the issue of religion and public education came to the fore. With grants from the Stone and Dodge Foundations, the R.E.A. took the leadership in forming the National Council on Religion and Public Education. A special issue of the journal, Religion and Public School Curriculum was edited by Richard Upsher Smith, who served as N.C.R.P.E. director. Beginning in 1979, a three-phase project on Faith Development in the Adult Life Cycle was directed by Kenneth Stokes. In 1978, the Association celebrated its 75th anniversary in Chicago and commissioned a book, A History of the Religious Education Association, by Stephen Schmidt, and an anthology of journal articles, Who Are We: The Quest for a Religious Education, edited by John Westerhoff, who had succeeded Dr. Miller as editor of the journal. Biennial conventions were held in cities of the U.S. and Canada in cooperation with the Association of Professors and Researchers in Religious Education.
Although predominantly Protestant in the beginning, the R.E.A. now includes Catholic, Jewish and other educators from the U.S. and Canada in four main categories: clergy, professors and researchers, directors and coordinators of religious education, and teachers in elementary and secondary schools.
Scope and Contents
The archives of the Religious Education Association represented in this record group consist of fifty-five linear feet of material dating from 1902 to 1988. The majority of R.E.A. records dating from 1983 to the present are located in the Association's New Haven offices. The material in this record group is divided into nine series:
The quantity of documentation available reflects the changing fortunes and activity levels of the R.E.A. Correspondence files amidst the designated series are most voluminous for the years 1952 to 1970 when Herman E. Wornom served as general secretary. These files reflect Wornom's style of extraordinary attention to detail involving extensive correspondence with numerous individuals recruited to assist in R.E.A. projects. For many years prior to Wornom's administration, the leadership of the R.E.A. was more diffused and in flux; this fact is reflected in the much less thorough documentation available for the early time period. Records from the periods before and after the Wornom administration are concentrated in the first four series of the record group. The vast bulk of the series devoted to regional work, research, and religion and higher education reflect the special projects of Wornom in these areas.
Received with the archives of the R.E.A. were documentation related to the National Council on Religion and Public Education and personal papers of the N.C.R.P.E. executive secretary, Richard U. Smith. These records have been placed in YDSL Record Groups 34 and 30 respectively. Boardman Kathan, General Secretary of the R.E.A. from 1970 to 1982, was instrumental in the formation of the N.C.R.P.E. in 1971 and served on its executive committee for several years. Though distinct from the archives of the R.E.A., the Smith and N.C.R.P.E. materials are important to an understanding of R.E.A. activities throughout the 1970s.
Other record groups at the Yale Divinity School Library complement the archives of the R.E.A. Most notable are the papers of George Albert Coe. According to R.E.A. historian Stephen Schmidt, Coe was the dominant intellectual influence on the Association until his death in 1951. Other personal papers of relevance at YDSL are those of Frank Knight Sanders, Hugh Hartshorne, Charles Reynolds Brown, Paul Vieth and Randolph Crump Miller. Also of interest in light of the R.E.A.'s involvement in the study of religion and higher education are documentation related to Yale's Religion in Higher Education program, archives of the Danforth Study of Campus Ministries, personal papers of Clarence P. Shedd and other record groups.
The chronologically arranged Organization and Policy Records of Series I provide an overview of the formation and development of the R.E.A. The documentation in this series should be examined in conjunction with the Committee Records of Series II, Secretarial Files of Series III and Meeting Records of Series IV to provide a rounded view of the R.E.A.'s evolving basic policies and programs. Of particular interest in Series I is material related to an investigation of the R.E.A. by the Institute of Social and Religious Research in 1925-1926. The published report and unpublished material gathered as part of this investigation provide significant documentation of the R.E.A.'s early years.
The Committee Records of Series II contain minutes, reports and correspondence related to the operations of the R.E.A.'s major administrative committees, its Editorial Committee and numerous short term committees established for specific purposes. Records of other committees such as the Research Committee, Finance Committee and committees to plan for national meetings are located elsewhere.
Records for the following administrative bodies are included in Series II:
Council of Religious Education (1907-1922)
General Committee (1924)
Board of Directors (1925-1982)
Executive Committee (1929-1983)
Nominating Committee (1916-1981)
Editorial Committee (1928-1982)
The Secretarial Files of Series III represent the general office files of the R.E.A.'s administrative leaders. The files include topically arranged collected material and writings but are primarily correspondence related to the general operations of the R.E.A. and its relationships with other organizations and institutions. For the most part, correspondence related to committee nominations or meetings, national conventions, regional work, publication, research, the study of religion in higher education and financial matters is located elsewhere, in Series II and IV through IX.
The Secretarial Files fall into three sections: the pre-Wornom era, the Wornom era, and the Kathan era. The Wornom and Kathan files represent integral files maintained for administrative purposes. The pre-Wornom files are an artificially constructed gathering of materials related to the numerous individuals who were R.E.A. leaders and administrators during its first five decades of existence. Material is notably lacking in this Series for the period prior to 1922; earlier correspondence is available amidst the Committee Records of Series II.
The amount of documentation available for Meetings of the R.E.A. in Series IV varies widely. In the section dealing with national meetings of the R.E.A., documentation is scarce prior to 1953 and extensive thereafter. The section on regional, co-sponsored or special conferences and meetings largely documents events from the Kathan era. Conferences specifically related to research activity and the study of religion in higher education are documented in Series VII and VIII respectively. Meetings of local R.E.A. chapters are documented in Series V.
As reflected in Series V, the stimulation of local R.E.A. chapters was a major focus for Herman Wornom as he entered office in 1952. His mentor, Harrison Elliott, had made numerous regional visits in the early 1940s; further plans for such regional work during Elliott's tenure as general secretary were foiled by his untimely death. Regional work reached its height during the years 1965 to 1967 when A. Wilson Cheek served as Associate General Secretary. The "regional round tables" on religion in higher education which were held in five cities during 1955-1956 are documented in Series VIII.
The somewhat haphazard collection of materials in Series VI, Publications, does not accurately reflect the important place of the R.E.A.'s publications in its overall program. Copies of the Association's journal, Religious Education and other major R.E.A. publications are in the Library's catalogued collection. The first publications of the R.E.A., its "Official Bulletins" are located in Series I. Records of the Editorial Committee are in Series II. Extensive materials relating to the planning and production of publications concerning research and religion and higher education are located in Series VII and VIII respectively.
Of interest in Series VI is the complete run of the periodical first called Character. The R.E.A. began publishing this periodical in 1934 under the leadership of General Secretary Joseph M. Artman. When Artman left as general secretary in 1935, ownership of the periodical was assigned to him in partial repayment to the R.E.A.'s indebtedness to him.
Series VII, Research, primarily documents two major R.E.A. program initiatives to stimulate and support research in religious education: the Lilly Endowment 5-stage project and the Faith in the Adult Life Cycle project. The Lilly project included a survey of research in religion and character education, a survey of problems in religious education, a series of consultations in 1959, a workshop held at Cornell University during the summer of 1961, and the formation of a Research Department within the R.E.A. which administered the Lilly Post-Doctoral Empirical Research Training Fellowships and produced the Research in Religious Development Handbook. The Faith in the Adult Life Cycle project is documented from 1976 through May, 1982.
The documentation in Series VIII, Religion and Higher Education, primarily dates from the years 1954 to 1959 and relates to a series of meetings on the role of religion in higher education. The R.E.A. sponsored "round tables" in New York, Chicago, and Boston which centered on the theme "The Responsibility of Higher Education for Judeo-Christian Values in American Culture." A Pittsburgh gathering on "Religion and Education for Professional Responsibility" was co-sponsored by the R.E.A. A meeting held in Minneapolis in April, 1955 was part of a long-range project, the Planning Commission on the study of the Place of Religion in the Curricula of State Universities, which was sponsored by the R.E.A. and the University of Minnesota. Also included in this Series are documentation of non-R.E.A. sponsored conferences and projects on religion in higher education, documentation of religion programs at specific institutions and a number of general articles collected by Herman Wornom.
The Financial and Promotional Records of Series IX date from 1930 to 1980 and are divided into four sections: Financial reports, Committee records, individuals who assisted the R.E.A. in raising funds, and foundation and corporate funding sources.
Arrangement
I. Organization and Policy Records
II. Committee Records
III. Secretarial Files
IV. Meetings
V. Regional Work
VI. Publications
VII. Research
VIII. Religion and Higher Education
IX. Financial and Promotional Records
X. Photographs
Religious education; Universities and colleges -- Religion; Educators; Artman, Joseph Manson, 1879-; Coe, George Albert, 1862-1951; Cope, Henry Frederick, 1870-1923; Dewey, John, 1859-1952; Elliott, Harrison S. (Harrison Sacket), 1882-1951; Harper, William Rainey, 1856-1906; Kathan, Boardman W.; Miller, Randolph Crump, 1910-2002; Sanders, Frank Knight, 1861-1933; Smith, Richard Upsher; Stokes, Kenneth; Strommen, Merton P.; Wornom, Herman E., 1902-1992; American Institute of Sacred Literature; Association of Professors and Researchers in Religious Education; National Council on Religion and Public Education (U.S.); Religious Education Association
- Organizational and Policy Records, Series I
  - Council of Seventy
    - Proposals re. formation of R.E.A., 1902 (Box 1, Folder 1)
    - Convention to form R.E.A., Chicago, 1903 Jan-Feb (Box 1, Folder 2)
  - Religious Education Association
    - Membership information; Publicity pamphlet; Official Bulletin No. 1, 1903 Feb-Aug (Box 1, Folder 3)
    - Official Bulletin No. 2, 1903 Dec (Box 1, Folder 4)
    - Official Bulletin No. 3, 1904 May (Box 1, Folder 5)
    - Official Bulletin No. 4, 1904 Sep (Box 1, Folder 6)
    - List of Officers and Members 1904-1905; Constitution; Report of Chairman of Executive Board, 1904, n.m. (Box 1, Folder 7)
    - Official Bulletin No. 5; Letter from Executive Board "A Brief Statement...", 1905-1906 (Box 1, Folder 8)
    - Annual Report of Secretary; "A Brief Statement..." Index to Publications of R.E.A., 1907-1908 (Box 1, Folder 9)
    - Annual Report of General Secretary; Declaration of Principles; Exhibit on Religious Education, 1911-1914 (Box 1, Folder 10)
    - "Twenty Years' Progress in Religious Education", by H. Cope; By-Laws; Policy statement; List of active members, 1923-1925 (Box 1, Folder 11)
    - Report of an Investigation of the R.E.A. by Institute of Social and Religious Research - Published report, 1925-1926 (Box 1, Folder 12)
    - Report of Investigation... Unpublished introductory material and Part I, "Objective Data", 1925-1926 (Box 1, Folder 13)
    - Unpublished Part II, "Opinion Data" (Box 1, Folder 14)
    - Unpublished Part III, "Recommendations..." (Box 1, Folder 15)
    - Unpublished Part IV, "Original Records" (Box 1, Folder 16)
    - Policy Statement (Box 1, Folder 17)
    - Memos re. unofficial conferences; Memo by Galen Fisher ;"Suggestions for an Exploratory Year...", by Harrison Elliott, 1931-1932 (Box 1, Folder 18)
    - Memos, policy statement; Minutes of informal meeting, 1933-1934 (Box 2, Folder 19)
    - Policy statements; Minutes of special local meeting, 1936-1937 (Box 2, Folder 20)
    - Memo re. membership; Minutes of informal meeting, 1938-1939 (Box 2, Folder 21)
    - Minutes of meetings; Policy statements, 1940 (Box 2, Folder 22)
    - Report of visits by Harrison Elliott and Ernest Chave; Committee of One Hundred, 1941-1943 (Box 2, Folder 23)
    - By-Laws; Publicity letters, 1944-1945 (Box 2, Folder 24)
    - Report of President; Letters to Board members, 1946-1947 (Box 2, Folder 25)
    - Report on NY R.E.A. group; Report from President, 1948-1949 (Box 2, Folder 26)
    - Mid-Century Expansion Fund; Appointment of Harrison Elliott as General Secretary, 1950 (Box 2, Folder 27)
    - Memos, brochure; Field trips by Harrison Elliott; Death of Harrison Elliott; Mid-Century Expansion Fund, 1951-1952 (Box 2, Folder 28)
    - Golden Anniversary, 1953-1954 (Box 2, Folder 29)
    - Form letters to members; Report; Policies re. forming committees, 1955-1959 (Box 2, Folder 30)
    - Reports, 1964 (Box 2, Folder 31)
    - Reports, brochure, 1967-1969 (Box 2, Folder 32)
    - Retirement of Herman Wornom; Installation of Boardman Kathan; Brochure; Policy statement, 1970 (Box 2, Folder 33)
    - Kathan Position Paper I and responses, 1970-1971 (Box 2, Folder 34)
    - Proposal re. future R.E.A. conventions and responses, 1971 (Box 2, Folder 35)
    - News releases, memos, 1971 (Box 3, Folder 36)
    - Membership survey, 1972 (Box 3, Folder 37-39)
    - Office relocation; Reports, 1973 (Box 3, Folder 40)
    - Proposed merger with CORED; Placement service, 1973-1976 (Box 3, Folder 41)
    - Future Planning Conference; Revised By-Laws, 1974-1975 (Box 3, Folder 42)
    - Brochure; Proposal for a Journal on Religious and Public Education; Project on Adult Moral/Values Development, 1976-1977 (Box 3, Folder 43)
    - Kathan performance review; QWS Management Study; Kathan position paper on future of R.E.A. Conventions, 1977 (Box 3, Folder 44)
    - Placement Service, 1978 (Box 3, Folder 45)
    - Brochure, reports; Statement of goal and objectives; 75th Anniversary Fund; Wornom Festschrift, 1978-1979 (Box 3, Folder 46)
    - Brochure; Kathan Sabbatical Report; Goals and objectives; Responses to survey by D. Syme, 1980-1981 (Box 3, Folder 47)
    - "Schedule of General Routine"; Brochures, n.d. (Box 3, Folder 48)
- Board and Committee Records, Series II
  - Council of Religious Education, 1907-1918 (Box 4, Folder 49)
  - Council of Religious Education, 1919-1922 (Box 4, Folder 50)
  - General Committee, 1924 (Box 4, Folder 51)
  - Board of Directors, 1925-1929 (Box 4, Folder 52)
  - Board of Directors, 1930 (Box 4, Folder 53)
  - Board of Directors, 1931-1932 (Box 4, Folder 54)
  - Board of Directors, 1933-1934 (Box 4, Folder 55)
  - Board of Directors, 1935-1938 (Box 4, Folder 56)
  - Board of Directors, 1939-1940 (Box 4, Folder 57)
  - Board of Directors, 1941 (Box 4, Folder 58)
  - Board of Directors, 1942, 1944 (Box 4, Folder 59)
  - Board of Directors, 1946, 1948 (Box 4, Folder 60)
  - Board of Directors, 1949 (Box 4, Folder 61)
  - Board of Directors, 1950 (Box 4, Folder 62)
  - Board of Directors, 1951 (Box 5, Folder 63)
  - Board of Directors, 1952-1953 (Box 5, Folder 64)
  - Board of Directors, 1954 (Box 5, Folder 65-66)
  - Board of Directors, 1955 (Box 5, Folder 67-69)
  - Board of Directors, 1956 (Box 5, Folder 70)
  - Board of Directors, 1957-1958 (Box 5, Folder 71)
  - Board of Directors, 1959-1960 (Box 5, Folder 72)
  - Board of Directors, 1961-1962 (Box 5, Folder 73)
  - Board of Directors, 1963 May (Box 5, Folder 74)
  - Board of Directors, 1963 Nov-1964 (Box 6, Folder 75)
  - Board of Directors, 1965 (Box 6, Folder 76)
  - Board of Directors, 1966 (Box 6, Folder 77)
  - Board of Directors, 1967 (Box 6, Folder 78)
  - Board of Directors, 1968 (Box 6, Folder 79)
  - Board of Directors, 1969 Jun (Box 6, Folder 80)
  - Board of Directors, 1969 Dec (Box 6, Folder 81)
  - Board of Directors: Minutes, 1970 Jun (Box 6, Folder 82)
  - Board of Directors: Minutes, 1970 Dec (Box 6, Folder 83)
  - Board of Directors: Correspondence, 1970 (Box 6, Folder 84)
  - Board of Directors: Minutes, 1971 (Box 7, Folder 85)
  - Board of Directors: Correspondence, 1971 (Box 7, Folder 86)
  - Board of Directors: Minutes, 1972 (Box 7, Folder 87)
  - Board of Directors: Correspondence, 1972 (Box 7, Folder 88)
  - Board of Directors: Minutes, 1973 Jan (Box 7, Folder 89)
  - Board of Directors: Minutes, 1973 May (Box 7, Folder 90)
  - Board of Directors: Minutes, 1973 Nov (Box 7, Folder 91)
  - Board of Directors: Correspondence, 1973 (Box 7, Folder 92)
  - Board of Directors: Minutes, 1974 (Box 7, Folder 93)
  - Board of Directors: Correspondence, 1974 (Box 7, Folder 94)
  - Board of Directors: Minutes, 1975 (Box 7, Folder 95)
  - Board of Directors: Correspondence, 1975 (Box 7, Folder 96)
  - Board of Directors: Minutes, 1976 Feb-May (Box 7, Folder 97)
  - Board of Directors: Minutes, 1976 Nov (Box 7, Folder 98)
  - Board of Directors: Correspondence, 1976 (Box 7, Folder 99)
  - Board of Directors: Minutes, 1977 May (Box 8, Folder 100)
  - Board of Directors: Minutes, correspondence, 1977 Nov (Box 8, Folder 101)
  - Board of Directors, 1978 (Box 8, Folder 102)
  - Board of Directors, 1979 May (Box 8, Folder 103)
  - Board of Directors, 1979 Sep-Nov (Box 8, Folder 104)
  - Board of Directors: Minutes, 1980 (Box 8, Folder 105)